<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations of present use concerning the danger resulting from the change of our church-government. By H.H. D.D.</title>
            <author>Hammond, Henry, 1605-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E344_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200971</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861573</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861573</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113711</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87016)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113711)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 56:E344[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations of present use concerning the danger resulting from the change of our church-government. By H.H. D.D.</title>
                  <author>Hammond, Henry, 1605-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>H.H. = Henry Hammond.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Also bound with copies of "Severall tracts", 1646.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113711:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113711:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONSJDERATJONS of preſent Uſe concerning THE DANGER Reſulting from the CHANGE OF OUR Church-Government.</p>
            <p>By H. H. D. D.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeere 1646.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113711:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113711:2"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS OF PRESENT USE, concerning the danger reſulting from the change of our CHURCH-GOVERNMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O Him that being ſatisfied in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopall Government,</hi> doth yet conceive that the parting with it is no <hi>change</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and conſequently, that the ſtanding for it at this time, when it is oppoſed, is but the preferring the intereſts of ſome inconſiderable men before the inconveniences and common wiſhes of all, I earneſtly deſire (in the bowells of compaſſion to my bleeding Countrey, and from a ſincere paſſionate wiſh that the <hi>cure</hi> of this dangerous wound may not be a <hi>palliate imperfect cure)</hi> to preſent ſome few ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, which I ſhall caſt under two heads (proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the two parts of the former ungrounded ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the one, <hi>That parting with the preſent Government is no change of Religion;</hi> the other, <hi>That ſtanding for it at this time, is the preferring the intereſts of ſome before the common wiſh of all,</hi> the peace of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Concerning the former, I offer to conſideration, Firſt, whether the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church be not a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113711:3"/>
part of <hi>Religion?</hi> That it is ſo, I ſhall make appeare by theſe reaſons. 1. That <hi>Government</hi> is as neceſſary to the <hi>preſervation</hi> of the Church as <hi>Preaching</hi> the Goſpell was to the <hi>plantation</hi> of it, and that therefore it was alwaies the Apoſtles practice, aſſoone as ever they had converted a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Province, or any conſiderable number of men in it, to leave it in the hands of ſome faithfull Perſons, to <hi>dreſſe,</hi> and <hi>tend,</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> what they had thus <hi>planted;</hi> and therefore though it were <hi>poſſible</hi> for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to be deprived of this benefit, and yet to remaine <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (as to <hi>want</hi> ſome limbs, or to <hi>abound</hi> to monſtroſity in others, is yet recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable with <hi>life</hi> and <hi>being</hi> of a man) to retaine the <hi>doctrine</hi> of Chriſtianity without any <hi>Government,</hi> to be a Chriſtian in the Wall or in the Wilderneſſe, a <hi>Stylita</hi> or <hi>Anachorite</hi> Chriſtian, (in which caſe there is no doubt the <hi>uſe</hi> of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Sacraments,</hi> inſtituted by Chriſts himſelfe, would not be <hi>neceſſary</hi> to <hi>Chriſtianity)</hi> yet would it be little leſſe then fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for any to deſigne or hope the <hi>proſperity</hi> or <hi>duration</hi> of a Church, or viſible ſociety of ſuch Chriſtians, without this grand <hi>neceſſary</hi> (though not of <hi>ſingle being,</hi> yet) of <hi>mutuall preſervation,</hi> this <hi>principle</hi> not of <hi>eſſence</hi> but of <hi>continuance,</hi> without which (it is the learned <hi>Breerewoods</hi> obſervation from S. <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> that the preſervation of a <hi>Church</hi> was once by <hi>experience</hi> found to be an <hi>impoſſible</hi> thing, no other engine being able to repaire the want or ſupply the <hi>place</hi> of that.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon may be drawne from the concurring <hi>pleas</hi> of all the moſt diſtant <hi>pretenders</hi> for the ſeverall Forms of Government in the <hi>Church,</hi> as well thoſe that have eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed the <hi>Papall,</hi> the <hi>Presbyteriall,</hi> the <hi>Independent,</hi> as thoſe which are for the preſent <hi>Engliſh</hi> Form by <hi>the King and his Biſhops, &amp;c.</hi> all vehemently contending for the neceſſity of that Government, which they affect in the Church, and none ſo calme or modeſt in their claimes, as the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Engliſh Prelacy; which moderation or want of heate, is ſure one reaſon that ſo many ſonnes of this Church are now tempted to thinke Government ſo <hi>unconſiderable</hi> a thing, and ſo <hi>extrinſecall</hi> to Chriſtianity; though this thought thus grounded, be a double injuſtice, 1. In ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113711:3"/>
that <hi>truth,</hi> for want of <hi>aſſerting,</hi> which is therefore not ſo vehemently <hi>aſſerted,</hi> becauſe it is a ſuppoſed <hi>truth.</hi> 2. In encouraging <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>violence</hi> of diſputers (the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt plague in a Church) by ſhewing them that the <hi>Eagereſt</hi> pretenders ſhall be moſt <hi>heeded,</hi> and that <hi>meekneſſe ſhall not inherit the earth,</hi> though both <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> promiſed it ſhould. A third argument may be had from the judgement of our <hi>State,</hi> which hath thought fit to make the <hi>Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the Church matter of one of the <hi>Articles of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and ſo to joyne in honour the care of it with the care of the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and to require as ſtrict a <hi>ſubſcription</hi> to the eſtabliſh't <hi>Government,</hi> as to the reſt of the 39. heads of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> by which you may evidently ſee, that to change the <hi>Government</hi> is to change the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and where Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Government both are changed, can we poſſibly think the Religion to be the ſame? I ſhall add no more <hi>Proofes</hi> of this, becauſe I conceive them <hi>unneceſſary;</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary miſapprehenſion being, as I ſuppoſe, not grounded by <hi>Arguments,</hi> but of it owne accord ariſing from an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an experiment,</hi> which many men, eſpecially <hi>perſons of quality,</hi> thinke they have made, that in their whole lives they never reaped any <hi>benefit</hi> from <hi>Government,</hi> never received anie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion or increaſe to their ſpirituall weal from that, as from the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the Church, they acknowledge to have done. To this ground of miſpriſion, as being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the cauſe of the whole miſtake, it will not be amiſſe to make ſome anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That many benefits wee receive from <hi>Government,</hi> which we do not <hi>viſibly diſcerne,</hi> and that therefore when wee <hi>diſcerne</hi> our ſelves to have received ſome growth, and cannot but know that it was wrought by <hi>meanes,</hi> wee ſhould rather confeſſe our want of <hi>ſenſe</hi> or gratitude to the <hi>true means,</hi> then imagine thoſe not to have been the <hi>means,</hi> only becauſe we have not that <hi>ſenſe</hi> of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That thoſe meanes which have been more <hi>viſible</hi> to us, the diſpenſation of the Word and Sacraments, have beene reacht out to us by the hand of <hi>Government,</hi> to which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we owe our acknowledgements in the ſecond place for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113711:4"/>
our <hi>preſervation</hi> and <hi>growth,</hi> as to the hand of ſupreme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence for our <hi>being</hi> or <hi>life</hi> ſpirituall.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That if the <hi>benefits of Government</hi> have not been real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly verie <hi>diſcernible</hi> and <hi>notable to</hi> all, that is not yet in any juſtice to be imputed to any <hi>defect</hi> that way in Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelfe, to any <hi>barrennes</hi> in the nature or particular temper of it, but to ſome <hi>default</hi> (which will deſerve obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and reforming) in the <hi>Perſons,</hi> either of the <hi>Rulers,</hi> or of <hi>thoſe</hi> which are <hi>under rule,</hi> or of a third ſort whoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it is to be the Rulers <hi>perſpectives</hi> and <hi>Otacouſticks,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to their <hi>knowledge,</hi> the wants of inferiours, which till they are <hi>knowne,</hi> are not likely to be <hi>repayred.</hi> The defaults in each of theſe ſeverals are, or may be, ſo many, and ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to common obſervation, that it will be much more reaſonable for each to reſolve to <hi>amend</hi> his part for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo to make it a buſineſſe of <hi>Reformation,</hi> then to charge the defaults of perſons to the defaming of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo to <hi>undervalue</hi> and <hi>ſcorne</hi> what our ſinnes firſt, then our phanſies have <hi>defamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The comfort is, that it hath been the <hi>clemency</hi> as well as the <hi>ſloth</hi> or <hi>cowardice</hi> of Governours, which have deprived men of the great fruits of Government, and if it may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed that it is very expedient, and will be taken in good part that Governours hereafter be more <hi>ſevere,</hi> as well as more <hi>diligent,</hi> more <hi>couragious,</hi> as well as more <hi>laborious,</hi> in uſing the <hi>Weapons of their warfare,</hi> to <hi>cut</hi> off or to <hi>cure</hi> without any reſpect of perſons whereſoever there is need of them; I ſhall hope this objection will <hi>then</hi> be throughly anſwered, if as <hi>yet</hi> it be not.</p>
            <p>A ſecond conſideration apportioned to the former head will be this, whether (ſuppoſing Government of the Church to be a conſiderable part of Religion) the change of it from eſtabliſhed Epiſcopacy to any other (namely to that of <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> by many without any <hi>Superiour</hi> over them, or as that is oppoſite to <hi>Epiſcopacy)</hi> be not a <hi>ſinne</hi> againſt <hi>Religion?</hi> That it is, or will be ſo, I ſhall endeavour to convince the <hi>gainſayer</hi> by theſe ſteps or degrees of proof, which though perhaps not each ſingle, yet all being put together, will,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113711:4"/>
I beleeve, where <hi>prejudice</hi> doth not hinder, be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to doe it.</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe this Government by <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſuperiour to <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> is of <hi>Apoſtolicall inſtitution.</hi> But this being an affirmation, as demonſtrable by Eccleſiaſticall Records, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing can be, or as the Canon of Scripture which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, is demonſtrated to be the Canon of Scripture, and in regard it hath by others been ſufficiently proved, I ſhall therefore wholly ſpare the repeating of that trouble, and adde unto it, 2. That it hath the <hi>example,</hi> though not the diſtinct <hi>precept</hi> of Chriſt, who with his twelve <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the many other <hi>Diſciples</hi> in time of his reſidence upon Earth, ſuperiour one to the other, are the copy, of which the <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> in the following age, were a tranſcript, who are therfore by S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> S. <hi>Iohns Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary,</hi> allowed to receive honour, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Presbyters</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the <hi>Deacons</hi> as the <hi>Seventy.</hi> 3. That as farre as concernes <hi>ſuperiority</hi> of one order to the other (which is ſufficient to eject the Presbytery which ſuppoſes an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>equality</hi> of all) it is authorized by ſacred Scripture-practice, where it appeares, that when <hi>Judas</hi> fell <note place="margin">Acts 1.</note> from his orbe of motion, the <hi>dignity</hi> of being one of the twelve, is by the direction of the Spirit, and by lot beſtowed upon <hi>Matthias,</hi> who, though before a Diſciple of Chriſt, was not till then aſſumed to that <hi>dignity.</hi> Fourthly, that ſuppoſing it to be in this manner <hi>Apoſtolicall,</hi> there is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle colour of reaſon to doubt, but that the preſerving of it is of as great moment as many <hi>doctrines</hi> of Chriſtianity, not onely becauſe many <hi>doctrines</hi> were not ſo <hi>explicitely</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Chriſt, but that they needed farther <hi>explicating</hi> by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> (and are therefore by the Church grounded not in any words of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> but in the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles)</hi> but alſo becauſe it was in Gods <hi>providence</hi> thought fit that <hi>Government</hi> ſhould be ſetled not by <hi>Chriſt perſonally,</hi> but by the Apoſtles, that is <hi>mediately</hi> by Chriſt; as doctrine was by Chriſt <hi>immediately.</hi> Chriſt in his life time gives them the ground of a Church, divine truth, the <hi>word of his Father,</hi> the acknowledgement of which is <hi>the rocke on which his</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113711:5"/>
               <hi>Church is built,</hi> on this the Apoſtles are to build, and gather members, and to ſettle the whole edifice <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately,</hi> and that they may not erre in that worke, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is promiſed to <hi>deſcend</hi> upon them, and Chriſt by that power of his to be with them in eminent manner, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to the end of the world.</hi> And <hi>Government</hi> being neceſſarie to this ſetling was undoubtedly thus referred and left to them by CHRIST, and ſo their Authority in inſtituting that which they inſtituted, as evidently deduced from CHRIST, as their power of <hi>Preaching</hi> what they preached, or <hi>baptizing</hi> whom they baptized. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gone thus farre, I cannot but reſume my <hi>conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> thus farre made more <hi>conſiderable,</hi> and appeale to any ſober conſcience, whether it be not ſome irreligion thus to diſplace or remove that which the Apoſtles (to whom only by Chriſt it was intruſted) according to Chriſts owne Samplar and Scripture-grounds, thought fit to ſettle in the Church, ſuppoſing it to be a matter of Religion which is ſpoken of, as before we proved; nay, whether if an <hi>Angell from Heaven</hi> were to be <hi>anathematized for teaching any other Doctrine then what</hi> one Apoſtle had taught, it would not be matter of juſt <hi>terrour</hi> to any that ſhould have any part in the guilt of inſtituting any other Government then that which the Apoſtles had inſtituted, eſpecially when the acts of <hi>Councells</hi> tell us, that what S. <hi>Paul</hi> denounces againſt the <hi>heterodox</hi> Angell, the Church did practiſe againſt <hi>Aerius,</hi> anathematized him for impugning this Government, which now we ſpeake of. And if ſtill the Authority of all this be blemiſht by this one <hi>exception,</hi> that this inſtitution of the Apoſtles is not affirmed in <hi>Scripture,</hi> or there commanded to poſterity to <hi>continue,</hi> and retain for ever.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, by ſaying that which may be a fourth Argument to prove the irreligiouſneſſe of ſuch change. That there is as much or more to be ſaid (in both thoſe reſpects, both for <hi>mention</hi> of this <hi>inſtitution in Scripture,</hi> and for <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall precept for continuing</hi> of it) for this <hi>Government,</hi> as for ſome other things whoſe change would be acknowledged very irreligious. I will onely inſtance in one, the inſtitution
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113711:5"/>
of the <hi>Lords day,</hi> of which there is nothing can be ſaid to the ſetting up the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>immutability</hi> of it, which will not be ſaid of <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> A <hi>ground</hi> of it there was <hi>in nature,</hi> ſome <hi>Time</hi> to be ſet apart to the ſpeciall publique ſervice of God; and the like <hi>ground</hi> there is <hi>in nature</hi> for this, that ſome <hi>Perſons</hi> ſhould be deſigned to, and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the ſpeciall publique ſervice of God. A <hi>patterne</hi> of that there was among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> one day in the ſeven defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for Gods <hi>Quotum</hi> or portion; the like <hi>patterne</hi> there is among the <hi>Jewes</hi> for this; a Government by <hi>High-prieſts, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Levites.</hi> That was an inſtitution not of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his life time immediately, but of his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> after his departure inveſted with ſuch power; the like inſtitution there is of this by the ſame <hi>Apoſtles</hi> after Chriſts aſcenſion, directed and aſſiſted by the <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi> The <hi>occaſion</hi> of pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the firſt day of the weeke was a ſolemne action of Chriſt his <hi>Reſurection</hi> on that day; the <hi>occaſion</hi> of this, the ſeverall diſtinct orders in the Church in Chriſts time, <hi>Chriſt, Apoſtles, Diſciples,</hi> and the manifeſt ſuperiority of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all of them (who affirmes himſelfe their <hi>Lord,</hi> even when he ſpeakes of his office miniſterialll, his <hi>coming to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to them)</hi> and of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> before the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now was ſhewed. The mention of that was found once in the <hi>Revelation</hi> diſtinctly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Lords day,</hi> and twice or thrice more in equipollent termes, <hi>the firſt day of the week;</hi> and the mention of Epiſcopacy is as cleare, <hi>the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Church of Epheſus, &amp;c.</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> (which hath beene cleared by irrefragable evidence to belong to this matter) and the <hi>Ruling Elder,</hi> in S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that muſt have <hi>double honour,</hi> and <hi>Titus left in Crete to ſet in order the things that were wanting, and to ordaine Elders in every Church;</hi> and many other more cleare mentions of the ſeverall titles and offices of <hi>Biſhop, Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Deacon,</hi> then there is of the name and duties of the <hi>Lords day.</hi> The <hi>obſcure men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of that in Scripture were <hi>explained</hi> in the writings and Stories of the firſt age of the Church, particularly in the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles</hi> of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and the <hi>obſcurities</hi> of the Sacred text concerning <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> are as clearely <hi>explicated</hi> and unfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113711:6"/>
by the ſame <hi>Ignatius,</hi> even in every one of thoſe <hi>Epiſtles</hi> of his which <hi>Vedelius</hi> (as great an enemy of this Order as <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> hath produced any) after his <hi>fiery tryall</hi> of that Author hath acknowledged to be his. <hi>The uſe</hi> of that continued from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time (though not ſo univerſally till the <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath</hi> was fairely laid aſleep) till theſe dayes in the <hi>univerſall Church,</hi> and all <hi>particular Churches,</hi> that wee read of; and the like uſe and practice of this continued <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally</hi> without any exception from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, till this day in the <hi>univerſall Church,</hi> as that ſignifies the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Church, and in each <hi>particular</hi> Church till about this laſt <hi>Century,</hi> and in this of ours from the planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpell till this day. Theſe are parallels enough to even the ballance (and I profeſſe to know no one more which might weigh it downe on that ſide) and to make it now ſeaſonable to-demand, whether it would not bee thought an act contrarie to Religion (whether that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies Chriſtian <hi>Piety,</hi> or <hi>meekeneſſe,</hi> or <hi>awe</hi> to all that is <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred)</hi> for any particular nationall Church, or part thereof, without any more warrant then is now offered for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent change, to remove the ſervice of God from the <hi>Lords day</hi> to any other day in the week, (which ſure is as ſmall a difference, as that betwixt <hi>Preſbyteriall</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment can by any be conceived to be) or inſted of our <hi>firſt day</hi> of the weeke to ſet apart either an <hi>eight,</hi> or a <hi>ſixt</hi> day, and ſo to change that <hi>Apoſtolicall inſtitution.</hi> If <hi>that</hi> ſeem ſtrange, or be ſtartled at, as unfit to be ventured on, or yeelded to, I ſhall deſire the ſame plea may be entred for <hi>this,</hi> and that conſcience may be ſecured, that either both are lawfull, or that the difference is cleare, and the advantage on the <hi>Lords dayes</hi> ſide, or that it may be reſolved that <hi>this</hi> is unlawfull as well as <hi>that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A fift Argument will be this, That the making (or yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to) this change, will be a ſcandall (very worthy to bee conſidered) in them that ſo <hi>yeeld,</hi> toward thoſe which <hi>oppoſe</hi> this Government as unlawfull; for this yeelding will be an appearing acknowledgement, that their contrary preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are true, and ſo a confirming them in their <hi>errour,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113711:6"/>
(which is no light one, but the ſame for which <hi>Aërius</hi> was and any other oppoſer would certainely have been anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized, and turned out of the <hi>Catholike</hi> Church for an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick)</hi> which is one ſpeciall kind of <hi>Scandalizing</hi> or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioning the fall of our Brethren, and withall a nouriſhing them in their <hi>uncharitable opinion</hi> not only of us, but of the ancient Fathers of the Church, (who were all <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> if this be ſo) which is another <hi>cauſing my Brother to offend:</hi> nay a kind of countenancing that <hi>unchriſtian</hi> (I am ſure <hi>unproteſtant) Doctrine,</hi> of the lawfulneſſe of <hi>taking up Armes,</hi> againſt lawfull Superiours and eſtabliſht Lawes, and propagating our opinions in Religion by that means, which perchance ſome may be betrayed to by this <hi>example,</hi> others brought to believe conſentaneous to <hi>Proteſtant Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> if they which are thus guilty be thus gratified; which as it were a <hi>change</hi> in our <hi>Doctrine,</hi> if it were <hi>really acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,</hi> ſo is it, in this reſpect, another act of <hi>Scandall,</hi> if it thus <hi>appeare</hi> to bee <hi>acknowledged,</hi> and that which would make any Heathen Prince unwilling to embrace our Religion, if this diſloyall perſwaſion were conceived to be a part of it.</p>
            <p>A ſixt Argument (which to me is of no ſmall force) I will yet but name, and referre it to others to conſider of, That no man is a Prieſt, or lawfully ordained Miniſter of any Chriſtian Church, but he that is <hi>called</hi> and <hi>ſent</hi> by <hi>God;</hi> that there is now no way in this Kingdome, to have that <hi>calling</hi> or <hi>miſſion</hi> duly, but from <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who are the only perſons who have the power of Ordaining others, <hi>given</hi> to them in their aſſumption to that Order, by thoſe who had it before, and can derive it from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who had it <hi>immediately</hi> from <hi>Heaven:</hi> and whatſoever other power a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> or <hi>Preſbyter</hi> may be thought or ſaid to have common with a Biſhop, it is yet the conſtant judgement of the univerſall Church, for 1500. yeares, that this of Ordination is not competible to one or more <hi>bare Preſbyters</hi> without a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and it will be eaſie to ſatisfie any reaſonable man in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be produced of ſound, or probabilitie to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie: and therefore if any Office, or Order, or Miniſtry in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113711:7"/>
the Church be conſiderable, this which is the ſtanding well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and ſpring of all the other, muſt be thought ſo alſo.</p>
            <p>Having premiſed theſe Arguments of ſo much weight, ſufficient to ſupport the burthen deſigned to them, I ſhall add, <hi>ex abundanti</hi> ſome inferiour ones, though they amount not ſo farre, as alone of themſelves to conclude it direct irreligion, yet to adde to the former heap ſome aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That to yeeld to this change, is to <hi>diſclaime</hi> thoſe bleſſed meanes of Gods <hi>providence</hi> which brought us to our Baptiſme, to all our ſpirituall life and growth that we have attained to, and that is a great ingratitude to that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is an act of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>inſolencie,</hi> to prefer any ſcheme of <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>Modern</hi> invention before that which the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> the <hi>Primitive,</hi> and (for ſo many years) the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church</hi> had authorized, and therefore I could almoſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to believe, that the framers of the <hi>Covenant</hi> had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged themſelves ſecretly to maintain Epiſcopacy by putting in thoſe words, <hi>[the beſt Reformed Churches]</hi> that I might eſcape thinking them ſo <hi>inſolent</hi> as to preferre any Churches before thoſe which they cannot but know have uſed <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It is a great <hi>tempting of Gods providence,</hi> in not being contented with that Forme which hath proſpered ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with us, and the whole Chriſtian World, (though ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (as all that is humane, or mixt with fleſh, is, even the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace of God in us) to be abuſed) and putting it to the adventure, whatſoever inconveniencies the next may bee ſubject to. Of the <hi>inconveniencies</hi> that Presbyterie doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly bring along with it, and the <hi>unreconcileableneſſe</hi> of them with <hi>Monarchicall Government</hi> in the State, ſufficient evidences have been given; and if there were no other but this, that the indeavouring to bring it in at this time hath brought this tempeſt and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> upon this Kingdome, and that this hath beene but the generall conſequent of that Government whereſoever it hath but begun to heave, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out Peace and obedience to lawfull authoritie toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113711:7"/>
it would well deſerve to have this marke of reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or non-election ſet upon it, if it were but for this, that the proſperity of ſuch attempts ſhould not encourage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the like. This and the like inconveniencies are of ſuch weight, that for men to be willing to exchange the <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> benefits of the one, for the <hi>uncertaine</hi> advantages and ſtrongly-probable calamities of the other, is a ſin that may <hi>provoke</hi> and <hi>tempt</hi> God to puniſh them yet further with greater and unexpected curſes, and therefore may deſerve in its place to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is is an Act of <hi>infidelity</hi> and practicall <hi>Atheiſme</hi> (for thoſe eſpecially who being convinced with the former rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to acknowledge any irreligion or ſin in ſuch change) to ſacrifice any thing to our owne preſent conveniencies, to make any change in ſacred matters, meerly out of intuition of our owne ſecular advantages; <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> in thinking that God cannot as eaſily blaſt that convenience ſo acquired, as thoſe many which came more directly to our hands; and <hi>infidelity,</hi> or <hi>diſtruſt,</hi> in thinking that God will not in his time give us thoſe conveniences and advantages (if they bee ſuch indeed) by meanes perfectly <hi>lawfull,</hi> which now we co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet by <hi>unlawfull.</hi> To which might be added the wants and omiſſions of thoſe duties of <hi>confeſſion of Chriſt,</hi> in not defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſtanding to thoſe truths which we are convinced to be ſuch, in time of their being oppugned and perſecuted; <hi>ſelfe-denyall,</hi> in not depoſiting our owne carnall ſecular aimes and intereſts, and <hi>of taking up the Croſſe,</hi> in not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring willingly and cheerfully when it lyes in our way to the performing of any act of obedience to Chriſt. But I would not inlarge to theſe, but only conclude this proof with a fift <hi>difficulty</hi> of ſeparating <hi>ſinne</hi> from <hi>changes,</hi> when they are great, and in matters of weight; It is the wiſemans advice that occaſioned this obſervation, <hi>My Sonne, feare thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them which are given to changes:</hi> The changes are ſure changes in Government, and thoſe are named indefinitely, without any <hi>reſtraint,</hi> and the verie <hi>medling</hi> with them <hi>that are inclined to</hi> ſuch, is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed both to Piety and Loyalty, <hi>Fearing of God and the King.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113711:8"/>
I have done with the conſiderations proportioned to the firſt part of the ſuggeſtion. I proceed to the view of the ſecond part of it, and there the conſideration ſhall be only this, whether,</p>
            <p>The change of this Government, be not a <hi>common intereſt of all,</hi> as well as of thoſe who are <hi>now Clergy-men.</hi> That it is ſo, may appeare probable, becauſe the <hi>revenue or honours</hi> which belong to them in Government are not the ſole, or main part of <hi>Government;</hi> there is a <hi>weight</hi> and <hi>office,</hi> which our fore-fathers thought worthy to be <hi>encouraged</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded</hi> with thoſe payments, and if any man ſhall thinke them ill proportioned, I ſhall not doubt to tell him S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomes</hi> judgement, <hi>that the burthen of a Biſhop was formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, even to an Angell to undergoe,</hi> and if the corruptions of latter times be affirmed to have changed that ſtate of things, I anſwer, that the reſtoring Epiſcopacy to its due <hi>burthen</hi> as well as <hi>reputation,</hi> were a care worthy of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and it is ſo farre from my deſire that any ſuch care ſhould be ſpared, that it is now my publike ſolemne Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both to God and man, that the <hi>power of the keyes,</hi> and the exerciſe of that power, the due uſe of <hi>confirmation,</hi> and (praevious to that) examination, and tryall of youth, a ſtrict ſearch into the manners and tempers, and ſufficiencies of thoſe that are to be admitted into holy <hi>Orders,</hi> and to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiate for <hi>publique Preachers,</hi> the <hi>viſitation</hi> of each pariſh in each Dioceſſe, and the exerciſe of Church-diſcipline up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all offenders; together with <hi>painfull,</hi> mature and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Catechizing,</hi> ſtudies of all kindes, and parts of Theologicall Learning, Languages, Controverſies, Writings of the Schooles and Caſuiſts, &amp;c. be ſo farre ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into conſideration by our Law-makers, and ſo far con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the collating of Church-preferments and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo much of Duty required of Clergie-men, and ſo little left <hi>arbitrary</hi> or <hi>at large,</hi> that every <hi>Church-preferment</hi> in this Kingdome may have ſuch a due <hi>burthen</hi> annexed to it, that no <hi>ignorant</hi> perſon ſhould be <hi>able,</hi> no <hi>lazy</hi> or <hi>luxurious</hi> perſon <hi>willing</hi> or <hi>forward</hi> to undergoe it. And if this might be thus deſigned, I ſhould then reſolve, that the direct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113711:8"/>
to the fore-mentioned ſuggeſtions would be truth, that the ſetling and continuing of this preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would prove the <hi>common intereſt</hi> of all, and onely the <hi>burthen</hi> of thoſe <hi>few</hi> that have thoſe painfull offices aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them; and leaſt any may think this word a <hi>boaſt</hi> (which I can ſafely venture with the world at this time, and not have reaſon to feare a <hi>ſurpriſall,</hi> or being taken at my word) I ſhall venture another offer in the name of my brethren of the Clergy; (not that I have took their particular Votes, but that I perſwade my ſelf ſo farre of their Piety.) That ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the <hi>Glory</hi> ſhould thus <hi>depart from Iſrael,</hi> by the Philiſtims <hi>taking the Arke of the Lord,</hi> laying waſt this flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Church of ours, or transforming it into a new guiſe, every one ſingle of us, that have any poſſeſſions or titles worthy any mans envy or rapine, and ſo are thought now by our own intereſts to have been bribed or fee'd Advocates in this cauſe, may forthwith be deprived of all that part of the Revenues of the Church wherein we are legally inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; and he that ſhall not cheerfully reſigne his part in the <hi>preſent</hi> proſperity of the Church, on the meere contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and intuition of the <hi>benefit</hi> that may now, and <hi>after his life</hi> redound to <hi>others,</hi> let him have the guilt of <hi>Achans wedge</hi> laid on him, and the charge of being diſturber of the State. I hope we have <hi>learnt</hi> to <hi>want as well as to abound,</hi> and to truſt God (that can <hi>feed</hi> the <hi>young Ravens</hi> when the old have expoſed them) for the feeding of us, and our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, though all our preſent meanes of doing it were taken from us, If this may ſerve turne to ſatisfie the <hi>thirſt</hi> of thoſe that <hi>gape,</hi> and the ſuſpicions of thoſe that <hi>look unkindly</hi> on us, we offer to free you from all blame of <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> ot <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> or <hi>injuſtice</hi> (from one of which, no other meanes imaginable can free a <hi>change</hi> of Government) by our owne voluntary <hi>Ceſſion</hi> or <hi>riſignation,</hi> as farre as our perſonall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts reach; and ſhall thinke the peace of this State, and continued proſperity of this Church, a moſt <hi>glorious</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, moſt <hi>cheaply</hi> bought, if it may be had upon ſuch terms as theſe. And if the Function it ſelfe, with the neceſſary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113711:9"/>
to it, be not ſwept away in the calamity, we ſhall be perfectly pleaſed whatſoever befall our <hi>Perſons,</hi> and deſire, that tryall may be made of the <hi>Ingenuity</hi> of Clergy-men, whether we have not thus farre <hi>profited</hi> under <hi>Gods rod,</hi> as to be willing to yeeld to any poſſible propoſition (which will bring no guilt of ſin upon our conſciences) toward the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the judgements of Heaven, which are now (I wiſh I might ſay <hi>for our ſinnes onely)</hi> moſt ſadly multiplyed upon this Land.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113711:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
